Hello everyone, welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
Hi guys, my name is Catherine.
大家好，我是Catherine。
And today we're going to be looking at another lesson as part of our sports series and this
今天我们要看另一节课，这是我们运动系列的一部分，而这次
time, well it's a debate.
呢，其实是一场辩论。
Is it a game or is it a sport?
它是游戏还是运动？
Oh, it's a sport.
哦，是运动。
You have to work your mind.
你得动脑子。
Yeah, so we're looking at chess, a very old, very popular sport, very difficult to play
是的，所以我们今天要聊的是国际象棋，一项非常古老、非常受欢迎、也很难玩的
as well.
运动。
It takes a lot of practice and believe me, it's frustrating at the beginning and I'm
它需要大量练习，而且相信我，刚开始时很让人沮丧，我现在
still kind of in the beginning and intermediate stages.
还处于初级到中级阶段。
But yeah, it takes a lot of practice and it takes a lot of time to familiarize yourself
但没错，它需要大量练习，也需要很多时间来熟悉
with the rules.
规则。
Right.
对。
So we're going to be learning a little bit more about the pieces and the rules today.
所以今天我们要多学一点关于棋子和规则的知识。
Okay, perfect.
好的，完美。
So we're not going to preview anything.
所以我们不打算提前预览任何内容。
Let's listen to the dialogue for the first time and then we'll come back and talk about
让我们第一次听对话，然后回来再讨论
the sport.
这项运动。
Bobby, come here.
Bobby，过来。
Look what I got you.
看我给你带了什么。
What is that?
那是什么？
A chess board.
一个棋盘。
Daddy's going to teach you how to play.
爸爸要教你下棋。
Cool.
酷。
Okay.
好的。
Each player gets 16 pieces.
每个玩家有16个棋子。
You can be the white ones and I'll play with the black pieces.
你可以用白棋，我用黑棋。
Now in the front, you set up the pawns.
现在在前面，你摆好兵。
Those are the least viable pieces and can only move one space forward.
这些是最不重要的棋子，只能向前移动一格。
When you're about to capture another piece, it can move one space diagonally.
当你准备吃另一个棋子时，它可以斜着移动一格。
What about all these other pieces?
那其他这些棋子呢？
See this one?
看到这个了吗？
It looks like a tower.
它看起来像一座塔。
It's called the rook.
它叫车。
The one with the tall hat is called the bishop.
那个戴高帽子的叫象。
See this little horsey?
看到这个小马了吗？
This is called the knight.
这叫马。
It's a very important piece, so it's best not to let your opponent capture it.
这是一个非常重要的棋子，所以最好不要让你的对手吃掉它。
And these two?
那这两个呢？
They are husband and wife.
他们是夫妻。
That's right.
没错。
That's the queen and that's the king.
那是后，那是王。
If the other player captures your king, he will say, checkmate, and the game is over.
如果对方吃掉你的王，他会说“将死”，游戏就结束了。
Doesn't this sound fun?
这听起来不好玩吗？
Nah, this sounds boring.
不，这听起来很无聊。
I'm going to go play Killer Zombies on my PlayStation.
我要去玩我的PlayStation上的《杀手僵尸》。
All right.
好吧。
So the kid is obviously not very interested in learning how to play chess.
所以这孩子显然对学下棋不太感兴趣。
Not at all.
一点也不。
You know, the arts of these kind of slower games might be replaced very soon by video
你知道，这类节奏较慢的游戏的艺术可能很快就会被电子游戏
games.
取代。
It doesn't really appeal to a little nine-year-old or ten-year-old instead of, you know, playing
它真的不太吸引一个九岁或十岁的小孩，而不是，你知道，玩
something like this versus, yeah, shooting.
这种东西，而不是，嗯，射击。
Yeah, exactly.
是的，没错。
But it's a very great game.
但这是一项很棒的游戏。
It's very difficult, like we mentioned.
它很难，就像我们提到的。
So we're going to look at the name of the pieces and the rules that are related to these
所以我们要在“语言要点”环节看看棋子的名称和与这些
pieces in Language Takeaway.
棋子相关的规则。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
Well, the first one you might have heard before because this is a word that is often used
嗯，第一个你可能以前听过，因为这个词通常用于
in strategy in general.
一般的策略中。
So the word pawn.
所以这个词是“兵”。
A pawn.
一个兵。
A pawn usually means something that is not very important that you can use to distract
“兵”通常指不太重要的东西，你可以用它来分散
an opponent.
对手的注意力。
All right.
好的。
So on the chessboard, you have eight pawns.
所以在棋盘上，你有八个兵。
So these are the ones that you have the most, but their movement is very limited.
所以这些是你数量最多的，但它们的移动非常有限。
So they can only move two spaces forward on the first move, right?
所以它们只能在第一步移动两格，对吧？
Right.
对。
Or one space after that.
之后只能移动一格。
One space forward.
向前一格。
And only when it's going to capture another piece can it move diagonally.
而且只有在吃另一个棋子时才能斜着移动。
All right.
好的。
So you can't just go diagonally.
所以你不能随便斜着走。
You have to go forward until you're going to take another person's piece to capture
你必须向前走，直到你要吃掉别人的棋子时才能
it and to go diagonally.
斜着走。
All right.
好的。
But a pawn is funny.
但“兵”这个词很有趣。
You can also use this word when you're talking about other things like, he used her as a
你也可以在谈论其他事情时用这个词，比如“他在他的小游戏里把她当成了
pawn in his little game.
一个兵”。
So you want to make an analogy.
所以你想做个类比。
You want to make a comparison from life to these games.
你想把生活和这些游戏做个比较。
You can use the word pawn.
你可以用“兵”这个词。
Pawn.
兵。
Very good.
非常好。
So let's go to the other pieces on the chessboard.
那我们来看看棋盘上的其他棋子。
On the very far ends of the board, you have the rook.
在棋盘的最两端，你有车。
Okay.
好的。
You've got two of these and they kind of look like towers from a castle.
你有两个这样的棋子，它们看起来有点像城堡的塔楼。
And it's a very, well, they're very important pieces and actually my favorite pieces because
而且它们是非常，嗯，非常重要的棋子，实际上是我最喜欢的棋子，因为
they're not very important at the beginning of a game, but at the end of a game, boom,
它们在游戏开始时不太重要，但在游戏结束时，砰，
boom, boom, you can do a lot of damage because they can go anywhere in straight lines.
砰，砰，你可以造成很大伤害，因为它们可以沿直线任意移动。
Right.
对。
So they can go forward, backwards, and to the sides, as many spaces as they want.
所以它们可以向前、向后和向两侧移动，想走多少格都行。
The whole board.
整个棋盘。
Yeah.
是的。
So easy, easy pieces to forget about at the beginning, but they're very important.
所以很容易在开始时忘记这些棋子，但它们非常重要。
And now next to the rook, we have the bishop.
现在在车旁边，我们有象。
Okay.
好的。
This is very different from the rook because the bishop can also go anywhere, but they
这和车很不一样，因为象也可以任意移动，但它们
can only go diagonally.
只能斜着走。
Right.
对。
So only diagonally.
所以只能斜着走。
They can also move four directions, but diagonally, right?
它们也可以向四个方向移动，但必须是斜线，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
So you can go forward and backward, but it has to be in a diagonal slanted line.
所以你可以向前和向后，但必须沿着斜线。
Okay.
好的。
And now next to the bishop, we have the knight.
现在在象旁边，我们有马。
Ooh, the knight.
哦，马。
So he's the one galloping on the horse, like those old stories of King Arthur we used to
所以它是骑在马上奔驰的那个，就像我们以前听过的亚瑟王
hear.
故事里的那样。
But the knight can go in an L shape and I've never understood this, but.
但马可以走L形，我一直没搞懂这个，不过。
It's weird.
这很奇怪。
So it can move two spaces forward and then one to the right or one to the left, or it
所以它可以向前移动两格，然后向右或向左一格，或者
can move two spaces to the right and then one forward.
向右移动两格，然后向前一格。
So it's very strange, but it always has to move three spaces and in the shape of an L.
所以非常奇怪，但它总是要移动三格，而且形状像L。
So I thought maybe he was the drunken piece.
所以我当时想他可能就是那个醉鬼。
He can go forward a little bit, then he kind of moves to the side.
他可以往前走一点，然后他会往旁边移动。
Right.
对。
So that's the knight.
那就是马。
It's actually a very, very important piece as well.
它其实也是一个非常重要的棋子。
And now the two main pieces maybe of the chessboard, the queen and king.
现在棋盘上两个主要的棋子，后和王。
So the king is kind of sad.
王有点可怜。
He can only move one space, but the queen is really the killer because she can do anything
他只能移动一格，但后才是真正的杀手，因为她什么都能做，
she wants.
想做什么就做什么。
This is interesting, right?
这挺有意思的，对吧？
Why do they make it like that?
为什么他们要这样设计呢？
The queen can move as many spaces as she wants in any direction, while the king can do the
后可以向任何方向移动任意多格，而王也可以向任何方向移动，
same in any direction he wants, but only one space.
但只能移动一格。
I think there's some similarity between real life now.
我觉得这和现实生活有点相似。
It's like the queen can do anything she wants and the king can kind of do whatever he wants.
就像后可以做任何她想做的事，王也可以做任何他想做的事。
Well maybe it has to do with the fact that he has to stay put and represent the country
嗯，也许是因为王必须待在原地代表国家，
and she can move around and move behind the scenes and has a little bit more mobility.
而后可以四处走动，在幕后活动，有更多的机动性。
Maybe.
也许吧。
Who knows?
谁知道呢？
Yeah.
是啊。
But in the end, the most important piece is the king, right?
但说到底，最重要的棋子还是王，对吧？
Once the king is captured, the game is over.
一旦王被吃掉，游戏就结束了。
Exactly.
没错。
So let's listen to today's dialogue one more time and slow it down a bit and find out if
那我们再听一遍今天的对话，放慢速度，看看
the boy understood any of these rules.
那个男孩有没有理解这些规则。
Bobby, come here.
鲍比，过来。
Look what I got you.
看我给你买了什么。
What is that?
那是什么？
A chessboard.
一副棋盘。
Daddy's going to teach you how to play.
爸爸要教你下棋。
Cool.
酷。
Okay.
好的。
Each player gets 16 pieces.
每个玩家有16个棋子。
You can be the white ones and I'll play with the black pieces.
你可以用白棋，我用黑棋。
Now in the front, you set up the pawns.
现在，在前面，你摆好兵。
Those are the least viable pieces and can only move one space forward.
这些是最弱的棋子，只能向前移动一格。
When you're about to capture another piece, it can move one space diagonally.
当你准备吃掉另一个棋子时，它可以斜着移动一格。
What about all these other pieces?
那其他这些棋子呢？
See this one that looks like a tower?
看到这个像塔的吗？
It's called the rook.
它叫车。
The one with the tall hat is called the bishop.
那个戴高帽子的叫象。
See this little horsey?
看到这个小马了吗？
This is called the knight.
这叫马。
It's a very important piece, so it's best not to let your opponent capture it.
它是个很重要的棋子，所以最好不要让你的对手吃掉它。
And these two?
那这两个呢？
They are husband and wife.
他们是夫妻。
That's right.
没错。
That's the queen and that's the king.
那是后，那是王。
If the other player captures your king, he will say, checkmate, and the game is over.
如果对方吃掉你的王，他会说“将死”，游戏就结束了。
Doesn't this sound fun?
这听起来不好玩吗？
Nah.
不。
This sounds boring.
听起来很无聊。
I'm going to go play Killer Zombies on my PlayStation.
我要去玩我的PlayStation上的《杀手僵尸》了。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
And now why don't we explain a couple of these phrases that we also use to explain the pieces.
现在我们来解释一下我们用来描述棋子的几个短语。
But let's look at some of these more in depth now in Fluency Builder.
但让我们在“流利度构建”环节更深入地看看这些。
So, Marco, one of the first phrases that we heard was the phrase to move diagonally or a diagonal line.
那么，马可，我们听到的第一个短语是“斜着移动”或“对角线”。
So, the pawns can sometimes do this and the bishop can do this, but what does it mean to move diagonally?
所以，兵有时可以这样走，象也可以，但斜着移动是什么意思呢？
Okay, so basically a diagonal line is not a line that goes straight up, right?
好的，基本上对角线不是一条直上直下的线，对吧？
Straight up to the sky, for example, or to the side, right?
比如直上天空，或者直向旁边，对吧？
It goes at an angle, so it's maybe going at 45 degrees or 30 degrees, so that's a diagonal movement or a diagonal line.
它是斜着的，可能是45度或30度角，所以那是斜向移动或对角线。
The next phrase we have is very strange, and this one you might hear from parents or children.
下一个短语很奇怪，你可能会从父母或孩子那里听到。
It says a little horsey.
它说“小马马”。
Little horsey.
小马马。
So, in many languages we have ways of breaking down words or adding to words to make them sound cuter, and this is one of those cases.
在很多语言中，我们有拆分单词或添加词缀让它们听起来更可爱的方式，这就是其中一种情况。
So, for example, little puppy or little kitty or kitten, these are words to make things sound cuter.
比如，小狗、小猫，这些词让东西听起来更可爱。
So, in this case, horse becomes horsey.
所以在这里，马变成了马马。
Horsey.
马马。
So, I want to ride the horsey.
所以，我想骑小马马。
It's a cute way of saying I want to ride the cute horse.
这是一种可爱的说法，表示我想骑那匹可爱的小马。
Mommy, mommy, I want to ride the horsey.
妈妈，妈妈，我想骑小马马。
Exactly.
没错。
So, baby talk often involves having these rhyming words.
所以，儿语经常包含这些押韵的词。
Mommy, horsey, doggy, puppy.
妈妈、马马、狗狗、小狗。
A doggy, exactly. Very good.
小狗，没错。非常好。
So, it's a cute way of saying something.
所以，这是一种可爱的表达方式。
And now, when we were talking about the chess pieces, when another piece takes or gets a piece, you say it captures it.
现在，当我们谈论国际象棋棋子时，当另一个棋子吃掉或得到某个棋子时，我们说它“吃掉”了它。
Okay. We say capture because, well, maybe it's a bit nicer than killing it, but capture means taking and keeping for yourself.
好的。我们说“吃掉”，因为，嗯，可能比“杀死”好听一点，但“吃掉”意味着拿走并占为己有。
So, we have a very popular game in America called capture the flag.
所以，美国有一个很流行的游戏叫“夺旗”。
Right. It's where you have to take each other's flag, right?
对。就是你要拿走对方的旗子，对吧？
You're stealing, essentially.
本质上是在偷。
You're stealing.
是在偷。
So, yeah, this is the term that is used in chess to capture another piece.
所以，是的，这就是国际象棋中用来描述吃掉另一个棋子的术语。
Sometimes, like, for example, in Spanish, we actually say, like, to eat the other piece.
有时候，比如在西班牙语里，我们实际上会说“吃掉”另一个棋子。
Really?
真的吗？
Yeah, you eat it.
是啊，你吃掉它。
Weird.
奇怪。
That's weird.
那真奇怪。
Well, we're a little bit more tame in those English-speaking countries, but to capture is a very important phrase,
嗯，在英语国家我们稍微温和一点，但“吃掉”是一个非常重要的短语，
and you're going to hear that in the news as well because you can capture a person.
你在新闻里也会听到，因为你可以“抓住”一个人。
You can capture a criminal.
你可以“抓住”一个罪犯。
All right, and the final word and the way that you end a game of chess, you say checkmate.
好了，最后一个词，也是结束一盘国际象棋的方式，你说“将死”。
Checkmate.
将死。
So, the game's over. Checkmate.
所以，游戏结束了。将死。
Well, there's two things that can happen at the end of a game, and, well, only one thing can happen at the very end of a game,
嗯，游戏结束时可能发生两种情况，而且，嗯，只有一种情况会在游戏真正结束时发生，
but you're going to hear these two phrases.
但你会听到这两个短语。
One is check, and the other is checkmate.
一个是“将军”，另一个是“将死”。
So, check means that I can take your king if I want to. Move.
所以，“将军”意味着如果我想，我可以吃掉你的王。走棋。
Right. It's in danger.
对。它处于危险中。
It's in danger, but checkmate is the end all.
它处于危险中，但“将死”就是终结。
It means this is the very, very last part of a game where you cannot do anything.
这意味着这是游戏的最后一步，你什么都做不了。
I've trapped you, and I win.
我困住了你，我赢了。
Right. Very good.
对。非常好。
So, the game is over when somebody says checkmate.
所以，当有人说“将死”时，游戏就结束了。
Why don't we listen to this dialogue for the last time,
我们最后再听一遍这段对话，
and then we'll come back and talk a little bit more about this very interesting game.
然后回来再聊聊这个非常有趣的游戏。
Bobby, come here. Look what I got you.
鲍比，过来。看我给你买了什么。
What is that?
那是什么？
A chessboard.
一副棋盘。
Daddy's going to teach you how to play.
爸爸要教你下棋。
Cool.
酷。
Okay. Each player gets 16 pieces.
好的。每个玩家有16个棋子。
You can be the white ones, and I'll play with the black pieces.
你可以用白棋，我用黑棋。
Now, in the front, you set up the pawns.
现在，在前面，你摆好兵。
Those are the least viable pieces and can only move one space forward.
这些是最弱的棋子，只能向前移动一格。
When you're about to capture another piece, it can move one space diagonally.
当你准备吃掉另一个棋子时，它可以斜着移动一格。
What about all these other pieces?
那其他这些棋子呢？
See this one that looks like a tower? It's called the rook.
看到这个像塔的吗？它叫车。
The one with the tall hat is called the bishop.
那个戴高帽子的叫主教。
See this little horsey? This is called the knight.
看到这个小马了吗？这叫骑士。
It's a very important piece, so it's best not to let your opponent capture it.
这是个非常重要的棋子，所以最好别让你的对手吃掉它。
And these two? They are husband and wife.
这两个呢？他们是夫妻。
That's right. That's the queen, and that's the king.
没错。那是王后，那是国王。
If the other player captures your king, he will say checkmate, and the game is over.
如果对方吃掉你的国王，他会说“将杀”，游戏就结束了。
Doesn't this sound fun?
听起来是不是很有趣？
Nah, this sounds boring. I'm going to go play Killer Zombies on my PlayStation.
不，这听起来很无聊。我要去玩我的PlayStation上的《杀手僵尸》了。
Pop quiz, Marco.
小测验，马可。
All right.
好吧。
The word check and the word mate, they both have meanings in English,
“Check”和“mate”这两个词在英语里都有各自的意思，
but put together, where does this phrase come from? What could it possibly mean?
但合在一起，这个短语从哪来的？它可能是什么意思呢？
I have no idea. Why don't you tell us? Because I seriously don't know where it comes from.
我不知道。你告诉我们吧？因为我真的不知道它从哪来的。
Okay, well, this is actually very interesting, because I looked it up, and I had no idea either,
好吧，这其实挺有意思的，因为我查了一下，我之前也不知道，
because we've always just said this, and it doesn't really make sense.
因为我们一直这么说，但它其实不太讲得通。
So I looked it up on the Internet, and I discovered that the game of chess is actually a very ancient game.
所以我在网上查了查，发现国际象棋其实是一种非常古老的游戏。
And it did not come from England, it did not come from France, it actually came from Persia.
它并非来自英国，也不是来自法国，实际上它来自波斯。
And in Persian, there are some words that kind of became the English words checkmate
在波斯语里，有些词后来演变成了英语的“checkmate”，
that mean the king is captured or the king is defeated.
意思是国王被俘或国王被击败。
Okay, so that's what it means. It doesn't mean the king is dead.
好吧，所以就是这个意思。它不是说国王死了。
No, it doesn't mean that he's dead, it means that he's been taken.
不，不是说他死了，而是说他被抓住了。
And so over time, the Persian word went into Arabic, and Arabic became French and English,
所以随着时间的推移，波斯语传入了阿拉伯语，阿拉伯语又传入了法语和英语，
and then now we say checkmate.
然后现在我们说“checkmate”。
Checkmate, okay, interesting.
“Checkmate”，好吧，有意思。
This is a very interesting word, and I'm sure everybody that's listening has a different translation for it in their own language.
这是个很有趣的词，我相信每个听众在自己的语言里都有不同的翻译。
I know, for example, that in Spanish, we would say jaque mate.
比如我知道，在西班牙语里，我们会说“jaque mate”。
Jaque mate.
“Jaque mate”。
Right, so I guess like jaque is something's in check, it's in danger, and then mate, kind of like kill.
对，所以我猜“jaque”是某物被将军、处于危险中，而“mate”有点像杀死。
So maybe it's probably not translated properly, because as you mentioned, it should mean defeated or captured, not killed.
所以可能翻译得不太准确，因为正如你所说，它应该表示被击败或被俘，而不是被杀。
So listeners, why don't you let us know how you say checkmate in your language?
所以听众们，不如告诉我们你们用母语怎么说“checkmate”？
Come to our website, englishpod.com.
来我们的网站，englishpod.com。
And also tell us if you have questions about the things we talked about today,
也请告诉我们，如果你对我们今天讨论的内容有疑问，
or if you want to share some stories of your own chess victories.
或者想分享一些你自己下棋获胜的故事。
Please get in touch with us on our website, otherwise you can email us at englishpod at praxislanguage.com.
请通过我们的网站联系我们，或者你也可以发邮件到englishpod@praxislanguage.com。
But until then, have a great day. Bye, everyone.
但在那之前，祝你们度过愉快的一天。大家再见。
🎵